Guide to the Thompson Coit Elliott Papers 1903-1937
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
- Historical Subject Files., 1765-1936 and undated; Series A; 90 folders
  - Sinclair, James, and William Sinclair, 1913-1936 and undated (Box-folder 4/4)
    Correspondence to T. C. Elliott regarding James Sinclair, Oregon Company clerk, and his brother, Chief Factor William Sinclair, both of the Hudson's Bay Company. Excerpts from documents in the Hudson's Bay Company archives, as well as Elliott's notes on the Sinclair brothers. Typescript copy of "Across the Continent Sixty Years Ago Early Travels of James Sinclair," Manitoba Free Press, 1913. Frank H. Woody's handscript "recollection regarding the abode of [William] Sinclair's in Hell Gate", 1914.
  - Smith, Jedediah S., 1911-1916 (Box-folder 4/5)
    Letters to T. C. Elliott regarding American fur trapper and brigade leader Jedediah S. Smith, the route of his travels up the Columbia River and to California, and members of Smith's expeditions. Also discussed is the naming of the Humboldt River.
  - Smith, Samuel DeWitt, 1908; 1919 (Box-folder 4/6)
    Letters to and from John W. Pullman to T. C. Elliott, including Pullman's handscript memoranda of the life of the Hon. Samuel DeWitt Smith, member of the Washington Territorial Legislature. Typescript copy of both is included. Notes from Lewis McNorris.
  - Spalding, Henry Harmon -- I, 1835-1839 (Box-folder 4/7)
    Letter from H. H. Spalding, Fort Vancouver, to Rev. David Green, Boston, 20 September 1835 (handscript, photostat). Excerpts from H. H. Spalding's journal, 1836 (handscript, photostat). Typescript copy of "Diary of Mr. H. H. Spalding", 1838-1839, from the Whitman Museum.
  - Spalding, Henry Harmon -- II, 1836 (Box-folder 4/8)
    "Narrative of an Overland Journey to Fort Vancouver and Lapwai in 1836 Together with an Account of the Beginning of the American Protestant Missions Beyond the Rockies" by H. H. Spalding (typescript).
  - Spalding, Henry Harmon -- III, 1865 and undated (Box-folder 4/9)
    "History of Indian Affairs Among the Nez Perces. No. 1. From Pacific May 25, 1865" (typescript copy). Lectures by Rev. H. H. Spalding, "Early Oregon Missions -- Their Importance in Securing the Country to Americans" (nos. 1-9, typescript).
  - Spokane Garry, 1820-1832; 1914-1917; 1936 (Box-folder 4/10)
    Correspondence to and from T. C. Elliott regarding Spokane Garry, son of a Spokane chief, sent to Red River Settlement for education. Photostat copy of letter from Cyrus H. Walker to Hon. Henry F. Ashurst, Chairman of Senate Committee on Indian Affairs, 29 November 1917. "Indian Account of the Settlement of Spokane County," Spokane Historical Society, 1916 (typescript). Excerpts from documents in the Hudson's Bay Company Archive on the topic "Spokan Garry and the Church Missionary Society's School at Red River Settlement"
  - Spokane House, 1911-1922 and undated (Box-folder 4/11)
    Correspondence regarding the location of the fur trade post Spokane House. Statements of James Mondahann, George Herron, and H. C. Burnett. Hand drawn maps of proposed sites for Spokane House.
  - Stevens, Isaac Ingalls, 1856-1857; 1919 (Box-folder 4/12)
    Materials regarding Isaac Stevens as governor of Washington Territory. Typescript copies of documents from "Message of the Governor of Washington Territory." "Transcripts and notations from Report of the Sec. of War, Jefferson Davis, dated Dec. 1st, 1856, 34th Congress, 3rd Session, House of Rep. Exec. Doc. No. 1 (Vol. II)" (typescript). Letter regarding copies.
  - Thompson, David, 1807-1811; 1908-1928; and undated (Box-folder 4/13)
    Correspondence, notes, copies of documents and draft manuscript regarding fur trade explorer David Thompson and his journeys through the Spokane country. "Narrative of the Expedition to the Kootanae Flat Bow Indian Countries, on the Sources of the Columbia River, Pacific Ocean by D. Thompson on behalf of the NW Company 1807" (typescript copy). Typescript excerpts from "Journey to the Lake Indian Country 1808" and other Thompson journals.
  - Tolmie, William Fraser, 1832-1886; 1916; and undated (Box-folder 4/14)
    Correspondence and notes, and typescript copies of documents relating to Dr. William Fraser Tolmie of the Hudson's Bay Company's Fort Nesqually and Fort Victoria. Typescript excerpts from Dr. Tolmie's journal of 1832-1833, when he first arrived in the Pacific Northwest.
  - U.S.S. Ontario (ship), 1874; 1918 (Box-folder 4/15)
    Correspondence to and from T. C. Elliott and notes regarding the ship Ontario, its log book, and journals of Lieutenant J. H. Aulick and Lieutenant David Conner.
  - Vancouver's Voyage, 1788-1792; 1914-1915; and undated (Box-folder 4/16)
    Correspondence, notes, and copies of documents relating to George Vancouver's voyage to the Pacific Northwest with the ships Discovery,Chatham, and Daedalus. Typescript copies of related documents, including "Portions of an Incomplete Journal" by Thomas Edgar, Master of the H.M.S. Discovery"; "Log of Captain of H. M. S. 'Chatham'"; "Captain George Vancouver's Narrative"; "Lieutenant Broughton's Account of Columbia River" (typescript copies). Manuscript draft for publication on the log of the Chatham.
  - Waldo, Daniel, 1878; 1918 (Box-folder 4/17)
    Daniel Waldo's "Critiques," based on Hubert Howe Bancroft's 1878 interview of pioneer Waldo in Salem, Oregon (typescript copy from the Bancroft Collection, University of California -- Berkeley).
  - Walker, Joel P., 1878 (Box-folder 4/18)
    "Narrative of Adventures thro. Alabama, Florida, New Mexico, Oregon, California etc. by Joel P. Walker, A Pioneer of Pioneers dictated by him to R. A. Thompson, Esq. of Sta. Rosa. Bancroft Library 1878" (typescript copy). Account includes Walker's 1840 visit to Oregon.
  - Ward Massacre, undated (Box-folder 4/19)
    Recollection of the 1854 massacre of Alexander Ward emigrant party, by an unnamed son-in-law of John Ward (typescript copy).
  - Whitman, Marcus, undated (Box-folder 4/20)
    Letter from Marcus Whitman to James M. Porter, regarding Whitman's views on the importance of the Oregon Territory (handscript, photostat).
  - Whitman, Perrin Beza, undated (Box-folder 4/21)
    "Perrin B. Whitman. A Stirring Recital by Dr. Whitman's Nephew and Son." (typescript copy; author unknown).
  - Whitman Controversy -- Correspondence, 1888-1922 and undated (Box-folder 5/1)
    Letters to and from T. C. Elliott regarding the historical contribution of missionaries Marcus and Narcissa Whitman and the transcription of Whitman documents for Mr. Elliott.
  - Whitman Controversy -- William I. Marshall -- I, 1882 and undated (Box-folder 5/2)
    Chapter 26, "Oregon," from Building the Nation by Charles Carleton Coffin, 1882. Handscript annotations in margins, by Marshall.
  - Whitman Controversy -- William I. Marshall -- II, 1893-1901 (Box-folder 5/3)
    Works by William I. Marshall on Marcus Whitman. "The Authorship and Value of the Account of the Migration of 1843 to Oregon Which Was Published as Part Two of George Wilkes' 'History of Oregon' New York, 1845" 1893 (typescript carbon copy). Manuscript draft refuting S. B. L. Penrose's defense of Marcus Whitman's place in Oregon history, as well as Appendices 3 and 6 to "The Whitman Saved Oregon Humbug" and Appendix to Chapter IX. (All documents are typescript carbon or mimeograph copies, some with the author's handwritten notation).
  - Whitman Controversy -- William I. Marshall -- III, 1901-1903 and undated (Box-folder 5/4)
    More works by William I. Marshall on Marcus Whitman. "Review of "Marcus Whitman and the Early Days of Oregon' by W. A. Mowry" 1902. "Is the Proper Basis of History 'Atmosphere' and 'Tradition' or the Study of Contemporaneous Documents? In Re Marcus Whitman" 1903. "Why His Search (?) for the Truth of History Was a Failure. Being a Review of Rev. Myron Eells' 'Reply to Prof. Bourne" 1903. Letter to General John W. Foster. (All documents are typescript carbon or mimeograph copies, some with the author's handwritten notation).
  - Whitman Controversy -- Other documents, 1838-1888 and undated (Box-folder 5/5)
    Notes and copies of documents regarding Marcus Whitman. Works by other historians, including "Dr. Marcus Whitman. An Estimate of the Services Rendered to Oregon by the Pioneer and Martyr," Frances Fuller Victor, 1884 (typescript), "Heroes and Heroines of the Long Ago" (typescript mimeograph signed C. G.), and "Undeveloped Factors in the Life of Marcus Whitman" by Archer Butler Hulbert (typescript carbon). Undated draft of speech by T. C. Elliott to the Narcissa Prentiss Chapter of the DAR in Walla Walla.
- Correspondence, 1908-1937; Series B; 10 folders.
  Letters to and from T. C. Elliott, on matters not treated in the subject files. Topics include publications, research, professional activities, and miscellaneous historical subjects. Also includes some draft manuscripts sent to Mr. Elliott by their authors. Arranged alphabetically by last or corporate name, and chronologically for each author. Many of the correspondents are booksellers, librarians, or other historians.
  - A-E, 1908-1924 (Box-folder 5/6)
    American Historical Association, James M. Ashton, James E. Babb, C. B. Bagley, J. Herbert Bainton, T. L. Ball, William S. Bell, John H. Benton, R. B. Berks, J. Q. A. Bowlby, Albert Britnell, J. B. Brooks, W. H. Brooks, Cornelius Brosnan, Burrelle's Press Clipping Bureau, Canadian Pacific Railway Company, Rev. William H. Clagett, C. P. Coburn, Katharine Coman, Neil S. Coventry, Department of the Interior [Canada], Asa Don Dickinson, Stella M. Drumm, and Allen B. Eaton.
  - Bancroft Library, 1908-1910 (Box-folder 5/7)
    Correspondence with Frederick J. Teggart and James R. Robertson concerning the York manuscript and other matters of interest to Mr. Elliott's research.
  - Book Purchases, 1909-1919 (Box-folder 5/8)
    Correspondence with booksellers regarding book purchases.
  - G-M, 1908-1921 (Box-folder 5/9)
    W. H. Gilstrap, W. B. Godfrey, R. E. Gosnell, Caroline Hathaway, Idress Head, Frederick V. Holman, Hensley R. Holmden, Franklin F. Hopper, A. L. Kirkpatrick, Henry H. Kohlhauff, Katharine B. Judson, H. T. Lockyer, M. S. McDonald, B. F. Manring, E. J. C. Markgraf, Sr., Archer Martin, Cornelia Marvin, Edmond S. Meany, A. G. Morice, Hugh Munro
  - Howay, F. W., 1930; 1934 and undated (Box-folder 5/10)
    Correspondence between F. W. Howay and T. C. Elliott, research notes, and manuscript, "The Lengthy Voyage of the Jefferson, 1791-1795," by F. W. Howay. Other letters from Howay to Elliott appear in the historical research subject files. The two historians collaborated on a number of projects.
  - Inland Empire Historical Society, 1909 (Box-folder 5/11)
  - Meyers, Jacob A., 1908-1917 (Box-folder 5/12)
    Letters to T. C. Elliott from Jacob A. Meyers, some including Mr. Meyers's research notes on topics relating to the exploration of the Pacific Northwest. Other letters from Meyers to T. C. Elliott appear elsewhere in the collection.
  - Northwest Indian Congress, 1925 (Box-folder 5/13)
    Correspondence regarding the annual parade of the Northwest Indian Congress in Spokane, Washington. T. C. Elliott was secretary of the Walla Walla Committee and Chairman of the Float Committee for Walla Walla.
  - N-Y, 1908-1937 (Box-folder 5/14)
    National Americana Society, North British and Mercantile Insurance Company, W. Y. Pemberton, S. H. Piles, Nellie B. Pipes, Wilbur F. Prock, Thomas W. Prosch, Mr. Root, P. H. W. Ross, E. O. S. Scholefield, Joseph Shafer, Smithsonian Institution, Omar C. Spencer, Gen. James Clark Strong, Benjamin Sulte, Reuben G. Thwaites, Henry L. Tolkington, J. B. Tyrell, United States Geographic Board, United States Geological Survey, L. Van Alstyne, F. P. Wagner, John T. Walbran, Mrs. C. M. Waters, J. R. Wilson, F. G. Young
  - Oregon Historical Society, 1908-1922 (Box-folder 5/15)
    Correspondence relating to business of the Oregon Historical Society Board.
- Ephemera, 1909; 1921; and undated; Series C; 2 folders
  - Association membership certificates, 1921 and undated (Box-folder 5/16)
  - Senate Bill 133, Washington State, 1909 (Box-folder 5/17)